Okay so it's time to set up your computer and install the necessary software for this course.
In this lesson I will show you how to install Python and configure your local environment so that way
we don't have to rely on the trial environment on Jupiter dot org.
I will show you how to install Python Anaconda on Mac OS.
If you're running a Windows machine check out the other set of video instead.
But before we begin let me explain what Python Anaconda is and why we're downloading it.
Anaconda is a python distribution.
And this means that Anaconda aims to provide everything you need for data science in one place.
It's essentially a bundle of software and code that makes it easy for getting set up for Data Science
and machine learning.
For example the anaconda bundle already includes the Jupiter notebook so you don't have to separately
download it and install it and it also includes tons and tons of Python packages and libraries that
we'll be using in this course.
What do I mean by libraries.
Well remember how we wrote import pandas or import Mac plot lib or import I learn in our first project.
Usually you'd have to download all these packages one by one before you can use them in your project.
But by downloading Anaconda we're going to be getting all these packages in one go that way we don't
have to worry about setup and configuration.
Later on in the course one word of warning though.
If you Google the word Anaconda you're probably not gonna get what you're looking for.
You'll want to search Anaconda Python to find the Continuum dot Io Web site or alternatively click on
the link in the lessons resources to be directed directly to the download page.
The thing about Python is it also comes in two flavors.
We're going to go with the newer version of Python.
Python 3 so while anacondas downloading this is a good time to go for a coffee or tea after the download
completes you can start the installation.
We're going to be presented with one of those standards set up wizards so we're gonna click next.
Then when I agreed to the license agreement for probably signing away our first born child at this point.
But on the next parts of the Wizard I'm just gonna go with the recommended options so I'm gonna seat
install for just myself.
And for the destination folder I'm also going to stick with the default power my computer actually isn't
as fast as it appears to be because I'm speeding up the video here but this installation process actually
takes a little while too.
So just be patient and after the installer finishes I'm just gonna click close and move to trash and
that's it.
Now it's time to fire up Anaconda and the Jupiter notebook just to see if everything's working click
on the little magnifying glass in the top right corner to bring up the spotlights search.
Alternatively you can use the command space keyboard shortcut to bring up the same thing then type terminal
and hit enter.
Now your terminal might be styled a little differently from mine.
I've made my text a little bigger and I've used the the black background so that's something you can
set under the preferences so if it's the first time you're using terminal you probably have it set to
the basic theme instead of hombre which is what I've got but hopefully that will make it a little bit
easier to read what I'm about to type and in this window type Python space dash dash version and here
you should see the version of Python that you've installed as well as the version of Anaconda and as
we've mentioned before.
Make sure the version of Python is three point six or higher next.
Let me show you how to start up your own Jupiter notebook.
You can do that by simply typing.
Jupiter
space notebook and hit enter.
Now give it a minute.
You should see Jupiter firing up in your browser.
Showing you the folder structure in your home directory.
And when you click on new you should be able to start a new Python 3 notebook so congratulations on
getting that working but starting up is only part of the equation.
Also have to be able to shut this down properly and to shut down open notebook go to a file close and
halt and you can log out and close your browser window.
But the important part is terminating the Jupiter notebook from the terminal and you can do this with
a keyboard shortcut.
You can see here in the instructions it says use control C to stop the server and shut down all kernels
twice to skip confirmation so on your keyboard press controls see twice you should then see the messages
shutting down kernels and that's how you close out of Jupiter completely.
Finally let me show you all the components that were installed alongside with Anaconda and to do that.
Let me show you the anaconda Navigator.
So go to your launcher and find the anaconda navigator.
Alternatively search for Anaconda navigator in your spotlight after it finishes loading.
You should see a window like this from here.
We can launch the Jupiter notebook or the spider Python I.D. or even our studio.
All right.
So congratulations on getting set up.
If you have any problems or had any issues ask in the Q and A section for this lesson.
I'll see you in the next videos.